once you physically secluded from from company
from company
from others
a practice of of some reflexive
questioning can really take take root
because there is a difference between
how how we feel when we are alone and I
will feel in the proximity of other
people it's a fundamental existential
difference and that's why that type of
solitude is necessary but for for an
economy rotational East understanding
any kind of meditation that it's not
about shutting out the world of senses
but it's about fully understanding it so
that it reflects your questioning it's
it's more of an attitude until it's
cause you don't mind then it is an
actual questioning in looking for
answers so once we are alone quiet
I can just ask yourself what is the mind
thinking right now but the point is
don't give the answers right away
don't jump you're answering and fill
this always thinking this just use the
question as as directing your own
attention towards the context in which
your mind is not those the particular
particular thoughts you might be
thinking and then let that context in
you let that question let the direction
revealed by question and you because
it's not really about the content of the
answer it's about discerning the context behind
it's about discerning the context behind
it so what is the mind thinking right
now while this talk is being listened to
why are you seated while you're alone
what is in the background of that what
thoughts what moves and learn how to see
them in that background on the level of
that background without overdoing their
analysis or rationalizing but you want
to see them as well because by not
seeing them and not rationalizing them
you'll be mystifying it you don't dare
either you want to see it on its own
terms and its own terms
a terms of the background and a degree
of ambiguity and less of the particular
clarity that's just the nature of those
fundamental thoughts to determine your
mood to then determine your particular
actions and so on
so what thoughts are present right now
you let that in do the mine start
slipping away if the mines are slipping
away you find something more defined to
think about as in what are my thoughts
right now how am I feeling right now in
regard to those thoughts what is my
fundamental mode what is my experience
as a whole and why am I feeling it
pleasantly or unpleasantly am i aware of
my situation right now that I'm in so
whatever thoughts might be coming up for
example you might be you might be
concerned about not being able to
maintain sufficient solitude or you
might be concerned that you might lose
the track of your mind once you get out
of the solitude then you start looking
into that further why why are you
concerned with the loss of this
particular composure what is concerning
about that
there is no right or wrong answer you
just want to see what's behind it what's
behind that concern hence the question
so initially you might have to be
holding yourself back a bit in terms of
trying to formulate the answer and
learning how to see behind the question
but in order to see behind the question
question as this is necessary for that
and that's why you need to know what
questions should be asked and in this
case the question is why would I be
affected by the loss of composure in the
mind so far based on my experience
throughout his life this mind of mine do
I have any say in its changing do I have
any say in its deciding this or that you
realize there is only a relative amount
of say overall you are kind of subjected
to the weathers of your mind
to the moons basically so why you
subjected to something that you're not
in control of again don't answer it
other question and let it in do that in
a year for a whole day if you need you
the whole point is allowing things to
endure on the level of these moods and
in discernment of nature of things
you're not concerned with a particular
content so why you subjected to
something they you are not in control of
you are not the subject oh so the mind
has its own moods arises ceases either
way 18 doers one way or the other yet
you were the one that's seemingly being
affected by by the unpleasant mood by
the pleasant mood you might be affected
now with the
of losing solitude or or not being able
to maintain the composure when you go
back into the world why is that
why is the loss of composure worried
because you might do something
unwholesome why is doing something
wholesome traveling
because they will clean it with remorse
or similar why's remorse problem because
it's unpleasant and above all because
it's not in your control if we were in
control we would never be remorseful or
sad or unhappy or disappointed which is
wouldn't so really the problem here is that you
so really the problem here is that you
subjected to these things of your own
mind of your own doing in a way but you
are not in control and that's so when
you are subjected to the disagreeable
that is your suffering then
so bottom line is then you don't want to
lose composure you're afraid of
compromise in solitude and my
compromised composure they might
compromise they're currently agreeable
state of mind
but if cutting the agreeable state of
mind were used to begin with he would
not change he would stay for as long as
you wanted to stay and you always want
to stay
nobody wants disagreeable and even
people want disagreeable things is
because they find that agreeable that's
just the most fundamental motivation
pleasure being happiness of peace anyway
point is agreeable so then all these
doubts you might have fears worries
about this about that about what if I
lose Mike mindfulness and then I say
things they then I regret to what I do
things or what if this piece doesn't
last as long is that what all of these
concerns all these particular
proliferations possibilities of these
concerns are all rooted in one one thing
that is here right now with you and
includes them all and that thing is you
don't want to suffer so see if that is
then the problem in all this particular
things you might be worrying about how
can you approach it
or rather what would be the better way
of going about it
so if losing solitude worries you
because you might go suffering losing
your mindfulness worried you because you
might result in suffering doing things
saying things thinking things worry you
because you might cause suffering
which is a better way to go in order to
try to understand this and overcome that
issue would it be trying to protect the
solitude would it be trying forcefully
or would full determination to never
lose mindfulness would it be never
saying they're doing anything they might
have said anyone Oh would it be freeing
yourself from possibility to suffer in
regard to loss of control in regard to
anything which is more likely to pertain
to the actual freedom from suffering
trying to manage things particularly
trying to protect your environment
trying to deal with it trying to deal
with remorse with things that come as a
result of you losing your control or
losing the sight of it or understanding
what's in common to all these things
which is you not wanting pain of any
kind so then the question should be
asked is am i right in pictures assuming
the attitude of not wanting displeasure
am i right in taking it for granted am i
right in holding it am i right in
maintaining it do I have a right to do
so
because attitude towards the possibility
of disagreeable feeling does imply a
certain entitlement from your point of
view you think you have a right to have
a say but is there really the case
because if you had a say in the first
place you wouldn't need to be wanting
anything things would just obey your
command your control your will but they
don't so you thinking you have a say in
the first place it's actually secondary
to the things themselves yet you
thinking you have a say kind of puts you
first and is that very discrepancy that
is the root of all the suffering
absolutely nothing else the Buddha said
well he never said that suffering is
caused because of this so because of
that or because somebody done something
disagreeable or we can get enough
available order all these things are
manifestations of suffering but
suffering in itself it's entirely
completely rooted in craving so presence
of craving presence of that discrepancy
that I'm talking about means presence
suffering so if then the discrepancy is
removed would you be able to suffer even
if things do appear is disagreeable
so that's the important distinction here
everybody who had the suitors day is
craving and suffering but it's actually
the point is discerning the the tacit
attitude that everybody has in still
assuming that say in things and by that
I mean say towards the like present
enduring feeling you have a say in it by
wanting it or not wanting it now
practically you know the feeling doesn't
obey your will whatsoever but that
doesn't stop you from still maintaining
that assumption that it should and that
assumption is maintained through
carelessly holding on an attitude of not
wanting pain wanting to get rid of the
arisen pain and the attitude of wanting
to prolong the arisen pleasure so it's
fine to not want pain but what it's not
fine is that within the present enduring
feeling whatever the feeling is to
maintain that stance decrease the
discrepancy in pleasure you want more
hence the discrepancy hence the
suffering in pain you want less you want
the absence of it but it's present by
you your attitude is attitude wanting it to
your attitude is attitude wanting it to
go so that's another discrepancy and
practically those are the two feelings
one can be practicing in regard to there
is obviously the neutral feeling as well
it's slightly harder to discern but even
within that you can because when it's
neither Pleasant nor
is distraction from that neutral
presence the discrepancy hence the suffering
the discrepancy hence the suffering
that's what we would have said that
neutral feeling if it's not known it's
felt unpleasant thing and you create a
discrepancy when you don't know that you
couldn't have created in the first place
so this is how every meditation should
go for yourself secluded contemplating
rightly asking the right questions and
then letting the direction relief are
revealed by those questions endure don't
jump into answers but Donovan mystify
and turn it into a brain fog you're
after clarity collective understanding
so through thinking about nature of
suffering you get closer to
understanding it you get closer and
seeing that you're concerned with
particular things that bother you is not
your suffering the suffering is the
presence of the discrepancy the you
created in regard to things that bother
you or in regard to things that don't
bother you because can you remain
indifferent in regard pleasure in regard
to happiness in regard to possibility of
pleasure and happiness
will you mind not remain not become
elated towards it will you mind not want
more of it will you mind try not to make
it stay forever can you remain in the
tub imperturbable can you remain
imperturbable in regard to pleasure
or can you remain in battle in regard to
pain can you remain mindful and composed
in reality neutral feeling or will your
mind turn and find something to do that
will distract itself from itself if the
answer is yes then you want others so
what do I do
what you do is keep bringing him back
into the mind these very things because
it's it's very ignoring of these truths
and characteristics of the behind the
motivations of your actions that's how
you maintain them and you ignore them
when you not see them and you not see
them because you ignore them so it's a
vicious circle but if you start looking
at least in their direction through
asking yourself the right questions for
the sake of revealing the direction
behind it then you're ignoring it less
and less and eventually you will become
unable to ignore it why because it's the
universal truth the Dhamma that said
what I said himself it's not a creation
of a theory as I'm just revealing the
nature of things that are there what do
you want them or not makes no difference
and for understanding the right nature
for which you need to have that right
instruction hence the right questions
then you will be unable to maintain all
the discrepancy or the sense of sense of
control and master things all the
various notions of I ever say or what I
at least imply having a say through my
attitude in regard to what I'm feeling
right now
so then whether it's pleasure pain
neutral feeling there will be no
discrepancy maintained by the mind in
regard to it and there is no discrepancy
is no suffering and there is in the
scene there's just a scene in the herd
there's just a herd and so on for all
the senses as the bahía Souter says
so what is my mind thinking right now
you can ask yourself that the answer is
if the answer is nothing specifically
that's fine that there is an experience
as a whole so what are the background
thoughts present in regard to your
nonspecific thinking right here right
now what's at the back of your mind
don't try to make it to the front to see
to the back but see what's what's in
that distance through that ambiguous fog
what is it what is he thinking
it's gonna be a general and biggest
thought don't over define it again but
don't ignore it either so if you don't
know how to relate to it see how it
feels are you feeling it regard to that
are you feeling it regard to that
thought at the background of your mind
Oh at the bedroom of your mind there is
a certain discomfort because of the
[Music] implicit pressure of the duties that I
implicit pressure of the duties that I
have to do in couple of hours time to go
to work or to do this after do that so
that's the background must you're not
thinking about it but it's kind of there
and you could see that that's being that
state of mind that mood is being felt
and it's perceived in that ambiguous
domain
so what you want to do is without trying
to over define it you want to learn how
to allow that discernment that
recognition to endure so you recognized
that there is a certain amount of
discomfort in the background of your
mind because of something you don't want
to do but you have to do so that's fine
but it's through not seeing it
you immediately default or rather by not
seeing it the starting point
the first attitude towards not something
that's not seen is not wanting it if is
disagreeable and wanting it if it's agreeable it's
and wanting it if it's agreeable it's
the discrepancy we talked about so now
you're discerning that the background of
your mind there is a so you you don't
have to like overly psychology you have
to rationalize it and explain this our
duties must be before none of that is
questioned here none of that is a
problem here we all must perform duties
we all have things to do the point is
your attitude in regards it on the level
of that background and the level at the
back of your mind
but you're not used to thinking about
things you only think about things that
are in front of you and in order to
think about something you need to bring
it to the front which means you're then
not seeing these little ambiguous
general backgrounds and moods that are
actually more fundamental than your
particular thoughts they are fuel there
are sort of directing you like like the
wind gently blowing into the sails it
might not be a very discernable or
strong wind but the point is there is a
constant exertion of its pressure
against the sea so you will be moving
the way it directs you and as the buddha
said the fundamental reason for being
directed by this discrepancy by the
greed aversion
is ignoring it ignorance of it not not
having it seen not seeing it not having
it seen not discerning it not allowing
it enduring that and develop clarity
regarded and when I say clarity I don't
mean to rationalize it and to collect
the data about it that's all secondary
to it clarity means whenever you look at
the background you will see it you don't
have to spend half an hour contemplating
preparing as a basically at will you
will see these things and how I develop
that you develop it to trying to see it
through clarifying the meaning the
context to clarify by clarifying that
the nature of it and then if the mind is
more composed and you have that clarity
in regard to the present enduring
feeling of discomfort because of the
pressure of duties and things you don't
want to do in two hours time so did you
create that feeling did it come from you
that feeling of discomfort No
so you found it there through looking at
the background perception so to speak
you discerned there is discomfort there
so you found it there which means he was
already there on its own so if something
was already there on its own you haven't
created it
you can't even conceive where it came
from as in oh it's because of this and
this and this no you just found it there
now you might rationally that it's
because of this this it is but all that
is secondary to the independent presence
present enduring of that feeling of this
comfort in regard to the duties that you
have to perform in two hours time so
something is just found there
independent of you
its origins pretty much inconceivable to
you what are you justified in having the
attitude of wanting it to go away
so out of the two of you you and that
disagreeable discomfort who who is more
right basically to be there whose
attitude is more correct the attitude of
that that discomfortable feeling is just
discomfort it doesn't want to do some
work or is it you feeling entitled to
not want it
who out of two of you is not minding
their own business
clearly that feeling is because it's
unaware of you so then it's you who is
not minding your own business it's you
who interferes with disagreeable it's
you who interferes with agreeable it's
you who interferes with neutral why is
that because you haven't fully realized
that you can't interfere in the first
place that the interference cannot
change the nature of things
presence of interference means presence
of suffering nature of things remains
the same
absence of interference means absence of
suffering nature of things
remains the same five aggregates of five
a great opportunity for another and
doesn't matter it's the same the
difference is the assumption in regard
to it
and that's all all a person needs to do
really there's no great revelation or
secret revealed and there was none
result in freedom them I know it's just
learning how to stop ignoring the
fundamental characteristics the nature
of things of your feelings your
perceptions your mood your detentions
that's it there is no like a perfect set
of perceptions and feelings you develop
bit by bit and then it culminates in
this great great manifestation no it's
actually undoing your perception because
everybody started the patina suka - Gina
cannot on the basis of you - Gina built
his own ship Peter Gina can become a
nutter hunt by undoing his state of
booty Gina
hence it's it's individually to be known
by the wise internally by undoing
yourself basically and that's why nobody
can do that for you and you undo things
you undo these gratuitous attitudes and
notions the result directly in your
suffering through understanding them
through discerning them why because the
basis for their existence is being
ignored that's what a VJ is and you
ignore something for various reasons but
the point is it's being ignored you
ignore something through through giving
in gratuitously through greed aversion
delusion which are all results secondary
results to the discrepancy the your
attitude fundamentally creates but now
obviously through taking for granted the
results of the discrepancy you carry on
the discrepancy that's why that's why
the sense restraint needs to come first
that we have to stop engaging with greed
aversion delusion in order then to
discern the attitude behind it
so if you can ask yourself now as you
move changed has you mood changed
whatever it's being felt before this is
still the same thing enduring there I
might see how it's slightly different
but overall it's the same so it's the
same thing and we gave the example of
say that discomfort because of something
to do after this does it bother you it
is comfort its discomfortable in itself
that does it bother you does it bother
you now when you have looked at it when
you've seen it when you're discerning in
the background in my bother you but does
he bother you as much as before do you
feel that pressure exercised over you to
the same extent as it was when you were
not aware or rather turning a blind eye
towards death which was pressuring you
no you cannot it cannot exercise the
same pressure that's the most apparent
thing that becomes visible to you a
direct release of the pressure a direct
immediate instantaneous release of the
burden now you might forget about it
and comes back but that's fine that just
how it works
so through repeating the motions of
discerning the nature of things rightly
they will result in you not maintaining
the discrepancy in regard to discomfort
or comfort you are gradually releasing
that pressure that's being exercised
over you that's why there is no greater
verification of understanding then
freedom from suffering that's why that's
the only verification you need even if
the whole world comes and says there
that's wrong you know that through
direct understanding of that you are
unable to suffer and that's what the
Buddha meant in the suitors that the one
with the right view even if everybody
comes and tells them no the Buddhist
really wrong his mind will remain
unchanged because even like no matter
what they would say that person for
oneself is directly incapable of
suffering he's not like running away from
he's not like running away from
interpretation there or having to
maintain some some determined meditation
technique to never say no he fully
understood it he's incapable of
suffering amidst the suffering whatever
he does doesn't matter
he cannot suffer and and there is
absolutely you cannot ask for a better
reward and verification that things have
been done rightly so that's the criteria
so all this questioning should be
resulting in freeing you from suffering
not rigged knowing not returning blind
eye on of try to shut things are but
through actually discerning the nature
then on the right level the level of
that background the level of the mood
the level of the feeling
so if the disagreeable feeling that we
gave is an example it's still there it's
still enduring you can start looking at
its characteristics
it is minding its own business isn't it
what do you think about it or not
doesn't matter that that feeling is
there enduring so you are the one who
makes oneself bother with it through not
seeing it there not allowing it to do
its forgiving Ingrid seriously to the
notion of to be get rid of
and when that general feeling whatever
he was changes you'll find a different
feel in there he wants your moment a
moment in between the change you're just
gonna now look and see oh that this
agreeable feeling is gone which means
now automatically something is agreeable
you don't care about what is agreeable
you look at the feeling so doesn't
matter how it's agreeable because of
this this and this or it disagreeable
because of this is what matters is is
they're agreeable feeling enduring or is
there a disagreeable feeling in the unit
and that's it there's no need for a
further answer let that question it has
revealed direction of the whatever
feeling is enduring right there let it
in you because through allowing it and
you you're allowing it well you are
allowing yourself to see its nature
which is independent of you you're not
in its control you cannot own it even if
you want it in a bubble you are entirely
invisible to it you don't exist for
feelings you don't exist for intentions
you don't exist for perceptions you
exist could you assume your own
existence that's why you Perdana it
manifests power the being so the five
aggregates feel completely invisible to
form feeling perception intentions and
consciousness where is any room for your
sense of self but when you have a
thought of me myself that has appeared
that's one of the aggregates that
thought so if your thought of your sense
of self cannot see you you're invisible
to it you realize that your own sense
itself is something that cannot be yours
it doesn't care about you and that's
what another really means that self
which I've been taking to be mine is not
mine that's
that's
becomes not so but the thing there was
self before and now it's not self is
still there the Buddha never said there
is no self there is not such thing them
no he said it's the five aggregates that
had taken itself so the thing that is
yourself is one of the aggregates
whatever that I agree it isn't time
doesn't matter and that's that whatever
was a problem and you're not saying that
what you have seen is in gratuitously
maintaining the ownership and face value
of that which has been presented as
myself failing to see that it's one of
the aggregates and as such you're
invisible to it which means your very
self doesn't know about you so how can
it be yours
learn how to let it endure for as long
as he wants to do whatever it is stop
trying to get rid of it through a
meditation technique
stop trying to ignore it stop trying to
distract yourself through sensuality
just recognize what's there in allowing
you